Arthur J. Cain Papers 1945-1988 Mss.Ms.Coll.63
American Philosophical Society
- Series I. Correspondence, 1945-1988; 33 boxes; 16.25 linear feet
  - Suzuki, David, 1978 (Box Series I-22)
  - Swales, M.K., 1955 (Box Series I-22)
  - Swann, H.K., 1959 (Box Series I-22)
  - Szarski, Henryk, 1972 (Box Series I-22)
  - Tanner, Robin D., 1986 (Box Series I-22)
  - Tarkowski, Z.M.T., 1974 (Box Series I-22)
  - Tattersfield, Peter, 1982-1987 (Box Series I-22)
  - Tatum, Jeremy B., 1978-1981 (Box Series I-22)
  - Taylor, C.J., 1971 (Box Series I-22)
  - Taylor, Dwight W., 1979 (Box Series I-22)
  - Taylor, Joan, 1986 (Box Series I-22)
  - Taylor, Myra L., 1983-1984 (Box Series I-22)
  - Taylor, R.C., 1979 (Box Series I-22)
  - Tchernov, Eiton, 1977-1979 (Box Series I-22)
  - Tenner, Edward, 1977-1982 (Box Series I-22)
  - Thake, Martin A., 1975-1983 (Box Series I-22)
  - Thayer, Charles W., 1978 (Box Series I-22)
  - Thom, William B., 1966-1968 (Box Series I-22)
  - Thomas, J.F.A., 1967 (Box Series I-22)
  - Thomas, Kenneth David, 1969-1980 (Box Series I-22)
  - Thomas, Michael Pugh, 1976-1980 (Box Series I-22)
  - Thompson, Fred G., 1979-1987 (Box Series I-23)
  - Thompson, Thomas Everett, 1968-1988 (Box Series I-23)
  - Thomson, Lansborough, 1963-1969 (Box Series I-23)
  - Thorn, Erik, 1956 (Box Series I-23)
  - Thorne, A.L.C., 1969-1970 (Box Series I-23)
  - Thorpe, Clifford, 1978 (Box Series I-23)
  - Thorpe, John, 1959-1981 (Box Series I-23)
  - Threadgold, Lawrence, 1979 (Box Series I-23)
  - Tillier, Simon, 2 folders (Box Series I-23)
    - Folder #1, 1980-1986 (Box Series I-23)
    - Folder #2, 1987; n.d. (Box Series I-23)
  - Tilling, Stephen, 1981-1984; n.d. (Box Series I-23)
  - Timmis, William H., 1972-1977 (Box Series I-23)
  - Tinbergen, Niko, 1965-1973 (Box Series I-23)
  - Tirmizi, Nasima M., 1974 (Box Series I-23)
  - Tober, K., 1978 (Box Series I-23)
  - Toffoletto, Ferdinando, 1974 (Box Series I-23)
  - Tombleson, P.H., 1973-1975 (Box Series I-23)
  - Tompkins, F.J., 1985 (Box Series I-23)
  - Tootell, David Charles, 1985 (Box Series I-23)
  - Tooze, John, 1968 (Box Series I-23)
  - Torrens, Hugh S., 1981-1982 (Box Series I-23)
  - Trevelyan, Raleigh, 1958 (Box Series I-23)
  - Trueman, E.R., 1975 (Box Series I-23)
  - Tsakas, Spyros C., 1985-1987; n.d. (Box Series I-23)
  - Tucker, A., 1977 (Box Series I-23)
  - Tull, A.G., 1961 (Box Series I-23)
  - Turner, Judith, 1976 (Box Series I-23)
  - Turner, Ruth D., 1976-1978 (Box Series I-23)
  - Unknown, 1954-1983; n.d. (Box Series I-23)
  - Usherwood, Peter N.R., 1975-1985 (Box Series I-23)
  - Utaiwi, Mahmoud Namous, 1986 (Box Series I-23)
  - Uzzell, Thomas, 1976-1984 (Box Series I-23)
  - Vacek, Don C., 1983 (Box Series I-23)
  - Vagvolgyi, Joe, 1979 (Box Series I-23)
  - Vail, Virginia A., 1977-1983 (Box Series I-23)
  - Valdeyron, G., 1975-1978 (Box Series I-23)
  - van Benthem Jutting, W.S.S., 1977 (Box Series I-23)
  - van Bruggen, A.C., 1970-1984 (Box Series I-23)
  - Van Damme, Dirk, 1987 (Box Series I-23)
  - van der Vecht, J. (Box Series I-23)
  - van der Veen, Ir. G., 1972-1973 (Box Series I-23)
  - van der Wart, Friedrich, 1977 (Box Series I-23)
  - Vane-Wright, R.I., 1980 (Box Series I-23)
  - Van Helden, Albert, 1985-1987 (Box Series I-23)
  - van Hoof, J.A.R.A.M. (Box Series I-23)
  - Varley, D.H., 1972-1974 (Box Series I-23)
  - Varley, George C., 1958-1968 (Box Series I-23)
  - Varndell, Ian M., 1979 (Box Series I-23)
  - Vasey, Colin, 1985-1988 (Box Series I-23)
  - Vaurie, Charles, 1968 (Box Series I-23)
  - Veale, Douglas, 1959 (Box Series I-23)
  - Vehrencamp, Sandra L., 1984 (Box Series I-23)
  - Verdcourt, B[rian?], 1983 (Box Series I-23)
  - Vermeij, Geerat J., 1977-1980 (Box Series I-23)
  - Vernon, Keith, 1984-1988 (Box Series I-23)
  - Vevers, H.G., 1974 (Box Series I-23)
  - Visser, M.H.C., 1983 (Box Series I-23)
  - von Cranach, Mario, 3 folders (Box Series I-24)
    - Folder #1, 1972-1977 (Box Series I-24)
      Ambrose, Anthony
      Chance, Michael R.A.
      Foppa, K.
      Hécaen, H.
      Leyhausen, Paul
      Masters, Roger D.
      Ploog, Detlev
      Rössler, Otto E.
      Schleidt, W.M.
      van Hoof, J.A.R.A.M.
      Wickler, Wolfgang
    - Folder #2, n.d. (Box Series I-24)
    - Folder #3, n.d. (Box Series I-24)
  - von Ullman, E., 1959 (Box Series I-24)
  - Vuilleumier, François, 1971-1977 (Box Series I-24)
  - Waage, Else-Marie Rüse, 1977 (Box Series I-24)
  - Wahl, Milton H., 1975 (Box Series I-24)
  - Wakeley, Philip C., 1983 (Box Series I-24)
  - Waldén, Henrik W., 1977-1979 (Box Series I-24)
  - Walker, Anthony J.M., 1980 (Box Series I-24)
  - Walker, Stan[ley], 1978 (Box Series I-24)
  - Wallace, Bruce, 1977 (Box Series I-24)
  - Wallace, Charlotte R., 1979-1986 (Box Series I-24)
  - Wallace, Ian, 1988 (Box Series I-24)
  - Waller, Richard, 1986 (Box Series I-24)
  - Walmsley, D., 1968 (Box Series I-24)
  - Walter, Michael (Box Series I-24)
    -See Ser.I, Collins Publishers
  - Walters, S. Max, 1979-1987 (Box Series I-24)
  - Ward, Peter, 1962; 1969 (Box Series I-24)
  - Wardle, Clement S., 1986 (Box Series I-24)
  - Warwick, Tom, 1977-1979 (Box Series I-24)
  - Watkinson, Anthony, 1977 (Box Series I-24)
  - Watson, R. Murray, 1965-1968 (Box Series I-24)
  - Watt, Ward, 1981 (Box Series I-24)
  - Webb, Charles, 1972-1980 (Box Series I-24)
  - Webb, Glenn R., 1983 (Box Series I-24)
  - Webb, S. David, 1985 (Box Series I-24)
  - Weightman, P., 1985 (Box Series I-24)
  - Weir, John, 1965-1966 (Box Series I-24)
  - Wells, C., 1976 (Box Series I-24)
  - Wertheimer, Douglas, 1972 (Box Series I-24)
  - West, Christopher, 1981; 1983 (Box Series I-24)
  - West, David A., 1978 (Box Series I-24)
  - West, Ian M., 1979 (Box Series I-24)
  - West, Richard G., 1968 (Box Series I-24)
  - Westermann, G.E.G., 1977 (Box Series I-24)
  - White, Frank, 1982-1987 (Box Series I-24)
  - White, Michael J.D., 1976-1977 (Box Series I-24)
  - White, Muriel E., 1977 (Box Series I-24)
  - White, Pamela, 1970 (Box Series I-24)
  - White, Peter, 1976 (Box Series I-24)
  - Whitelaw, James J., 1981 (Box Series I-24)
  - Whittaker, John B., 1976-1977 (Box Series I-24)
  - Whitten, Max[well John], 1970; 1975 (Box Series I-24)
  - Wickler, Wolfgang, 1979 (Box Series I-24)
  - Wiggins, Glenn B., 1977 (Box Series I-24)
  - Wight, W.J., 1976 (Box Series I-24)
  - Wilkes, W.E., 1980 (Box Series I-24)
  - Wilkinson, Chris, 1968-1980 (Box Series I-24)
  - Williams, Carolyn, 1971-1972 (Box Series I-25)
  - Williams, Ernest E., 1976 (Box Series I-25)
  - Williams, Gray, 1984-1988; n.d. (Box Series I-25)
  - Williams, Stan, 1984 (Box Series I-25)
  - Williamson, J.M., 1977 (Box Series I-25)
  - Williamson, Mark H., 1962-1983; n.d. (Box Series I-25)
  - Williamson, P.G. (Box Series I-25)
    -See Ser.I, Futuyma, Douglas J.
  - Williamson, Phillip, 1969-1980 (Box Series I-25)
  - Willmer, E.N., 1969-1979 (Box Series I-25)
  - Wilson, Averil, 1988 (Box Series I-25)
  - Wilson, Don E., 1971 (Box Series I-25)
  - Wilson, E.O., 1975; 1988 (Box Series I-25)
  - Wilson, Peter, 1984 (Box Series I-25)
  - Wilson, Rod L., 1984 (Box Series I-25)
  - Winsor, Mary P., 1985-1986; n.d. (Box Series I-25)
  - Winter, Alan, 1971-1972 (Box Series I-25)
  - Withy, R.M., 1976 (Box Series I-25)
  - Wolda, Henk, 1962-1972 (Box Series I-25)
  - Wolfarth, P.J., 1968 (Box Series I-25)
  - Wood, Alison, 1988 (Box Series I-25)
  - Wood, B.A., 1979-1986 (Box Series I-25)
  - Wood, Roger J., 1972-1975 (Box Series I-25)
  - Woodford, H., 1977 (Box Series I-25)
  - Woodford, V., 1970 (Box Series I-25)
  - Woodley, Jeremy David, 1958-1980; n.d. (Box Series I-25)
  - Woodruff, David S, 3 folders (Box Series I-25)
    - Folder #1, 1975-1985 (Box Series I-25)
    - Folder #2, 1986 (Box Series I-25)
    - Folder #3, n.d. (Box Series I-25)
  - Woodward, F.R., 1986 (Box Series I-25)
  - Wool, David, 1985 (Box Series I-25)
  - Worrall, John, 1979 (Box Series I-25)
  - Wright, Jonathan, 1987 (Box Series I-25)
  - Wright, Sewall, 1970; 1981; 2.0 Item(s) (Box Series I-25)
    -See also Ser.I, Provine, William B.
  - Wye, A.J., 1979 (Box Series I-25)
  - Wynne-Edwards, V.C., 1978 (Box Series I-25)
  - Xiotiris, N.I., 1984 (Box Series I-25)
  - Yalden, Derek W., 1972-1975 (Box Series I-25)
  - Yochelson, Ellis, 1977-1979; n.d. (Box Series I-25)
  - Yom-Tov, Yoram, 1970-1988 (Box Series I-25)
  - Yonge, Maurice, 1978 (Box Series I-25)
  - York, Richard C., 1969 (Box Series I-25)
  - Young, Charles G., 1960 (Box Series I-25)
  - Young, David, 1973-1980 (Box Series I-25)
  - Young, J. Peter W., 1977 (Box Series I-25)
  - Zahavi, Amotz, 1977-1978 (Box Series I-25)
  - Zaina, L.A., 1986 (Box Series I-25)
  - Zilch, A., 1977 (Box Series I-25)
- Series II. Subject files, 1951-1988; 6 boxes; 3 linear feet
  Materials which highlight the major scientific activities and accomplishments of Cain's career. The series is arranged alphabetically by subject; each subject file contains a variety of documents, including material such as minutes, reports, programs, graphs, maps, and miscellaneous research data.
  A small amount of correspondence which originally appeared in the subject files has been added to Series I under the correspondents' names. Researchers interested in the following subject files are advised of related material to be found in Series I:
  Series II, Animal Breeding Research Organization -- see also Series I, Sheppard, Philip M.
  Series II, Hutchinson University Library -- see also Series I, Douglas, Ann (editor)
  Series II, Science Research Council grant -- see also Series I, Arnold, Richard W.
  Cain and Sheppard (whose papers are also housed in the APS Library) were both members of the Agricultural Research Council of the Animal Breeding Research Organization; consequently, information on this group is available within a subject file as well as Sheppard's correspondence file. Hutchinson University Library, responsible for the publication of Cain's Animal Species and Their Evolution, also retained Cain as an editor of their Biological Series from 1967-1975; much of Cain's correspondence with their editor, Ann Douglas, involves his reviews. Finally, details regarding the Science Research Council (SRC) grant received by Cain are located in a subject file as well as the correspondence file of his Senior Research Officer/Associate, Richard W. Arnold.
  Subject files often record Cain's membership and participation in professional societies and organizations such as the Animal Breeding Research Organization (1965-1968), Genetical Society (1979-1985), Institute of Biology (1964-1977), Population Genetics Group (1967-1988), Serengeti Research Institute (1965-1969), and Systematics Association (1963-1984). These files generally document business such as minutes, reports, and programs of meetings. Other subject files exist for biological conferences and meetings attended by Cain. In many cases, files such as these contain papers given by Cain as well as colleagues at symposia. These papers remain within the subject file they were originally found. Other material within subject files for scientific meetings includes programs, lists of attendees, and notes taken by Cain.
  Other subject files of note include the British Guiana Expedition (1952-1959) and the Science Research Council grant (1961-968). The former, an Oxford expedition conducted in 1959, holds preparatory material in the form of notes and reports. The latter involves a grant to study functional systematics through natural selection in the wild (particularly involving Cepaea) and contains detailed documents of the grant application process and reports as the research progressed.
  - Academy of Natural Sciences Bicentennial Symposium, 1976 (Box Series II-1)
  - Ainsdale Sand Dunes National Nature Reserve (Box Series II-1)
  - Angola. Expeditions to, 1954-1961 (Box Series II-1)
  - Animal Breeding Research Organization, 1965-1968; n.d. (Box Series II-1)
  - Arctic Norway Expedition. Report to the Oxford, 1960 (Box Series II-1)
  - Bio-Probe, 1966 (Box Series II-1)
  - Biosystematics of Haematophagous insects. Symposium on the, 1987 (Box Series II-1)
  - British Guiana Expedition, 1952-1959; n.d. (Box Series II-1)
  - British Solomon Islands. Folder #1, 1953-1959; n.d. (Box Series II-1)
  - British Solomon Islands. Folder #2, 1965 (Box Series II-1)
  - Canada, 1977 (Box Series II-1)
  - Congrès International de Zoologie. 17th, 1972 (Box Series II-1)
  - Curriculum vitae, [ca. 1975?]; 14.0 p. (Box Series II-1)
    Bibliographical matters; Biographical and personal data
  - Diary, 1968 (Box Series II-1)
  - Ecological Genetics Group, 1967-1981; 7.0 Item(s) (Box Series II-1)
    Conferences and symposia; Ecology; Genetics; Genetics -- Snails; Genetics of plants; Scientific organizations, meetings, programs
  - Ecology and Genetics of Natural Snail Populations. International Conference on the, 1962 (Box Series II-1)
    Conferences and symposia; Genetics -- Snails; Population genetics -- Snails; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Edward Grey Institute Conference on Bird Biology, 1970-1971; n.d. (Box Series II-1)
  - Edward Grey Institute Conference [on] Birds as Predators, 1974 (Box Series II-1)
  - Endoskeletal System in Arthropoda (Box Series II-1)
  - European Conservation Year, 1969 (Box Series II-1)
  - Evolution, 1961-1962 (Box Series II-1)
  - Filing System. Review of AJC's, 1982 (Box Series II-1)
  - Galapagos Survey. IUCN-UNESCO, 1957-1958 (Box Series II-2)
  - Genetical Society, 1979-1985; 2 folders (Box Series II-2)
    Business; Committee activities; Conferences and symposia; Genetics Society (Great Britain) -- London; Publication; Scientific organizations, meetings, programs
    - Folder #1, 1979-1981 (Box Series II-2)
    - Folder #2, 1982-1985 (Box Series II-2)
  - Gibraltar, 1975 (Box Series II-2)
  - Hutchison University Library, 1951-1972; n.d. (Box Series II-2)
  - Hutchison University Library. Royalty Statements, 1954-1965 (Box Series II-2)
  - Inbreeding Effects in Japan. Exhibit on, n.d. (Box Series II-2)
  - Institute of Biology, 2 folders (Box Series II-2)
    - Folder #1, 1964-1974 (Box Series II-2)
    - Folder #2, 1975-1977, n.d. (Box Series II-2)
  - Island of Muck. Expedition to the (Box Series II-2)
  - Lectures and Seminars by AJC. List of, 1964-1966 (Box Series II-2)
  - Linnean Society of London, 1968 (Box Series II-2)
  - Liverpool Polytechnic Symposium [on] Speciation, 1971 (Box Series II-2)
  - Lumbricidae. Key to the, n.d. (Box Series II-2)
  - Macoma, 1985 (Box Series II-2)
  - Malacological Congress. Ninth International, 1986 (Box Series II-2)
  - Mammal Society, 1968 (Box Series II-2)
  - Meeting Programs. Miscellaneous, 1976-1982 (Box Series II-2)
  - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box Series II-2)
  - Miscellaneous Data, n.d. (Box Series II-2)
  - Nigeria. British Museum Collecting Expedition to, 1962 (Box Series II-3)
  - Notecards. Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box Series II-3)
  - Nuffield Unit of Medical Genetics. Liverpool University, 1965-1972 (Box Series II-3)
  - Population Genetics Group, 1967-1988; 2 folders (Box Series II-3)
    Business; Conferences and symposia; Drosophila genetics; Evolution; Genetics -- Snails; Population genetics; Scientific organizations, meetings, programs; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
    - Folder #1, 1967-1974 (Box Series II-3)
    - Folder #2, 1975-1988 (Box Series II-3)
  - Population Studies of Polymorphic Snails. Conference on, 1966-1967; 2 folders (Box Series II-3)
    - Folder #1, 1966-1967; n.d. (Box Series II-3)
    - Folder #2, n.d. (Box Series II-3)
  - A Preliminary Study of the Soils of an Area Between the Potaro and Kuribrong Rivers, British Guiana, 1962 (Box Series II-3)
  - The Preservation of Man's Environment, 1970 (Box Series II-3)
  - Publications. List of, 1964 (Box Series II-3)
  - Reprints. Requests for, n.d. (Box Series II-3)
  - Reviews, 1954-1985 (Box Series II-3)
  - Royal Society, 1966 (Box Series II-3)
  - Royal Society Expeditions, 1962-1965 (Box Series II-3)
  - Royal Society Tree-Climbing Gear, n.d. (Box Series II-3)
  - Science Research Council, 5 folders (Box Series II-4)
    - Scholarship Committee, 1974-1975 (Box Series II-4)
    - Grant, Folder #1 (Box Series II-4)
    - Grant, Folder #2, 1961-1968 (Box Series II-4)
    - Grant, Folder #3 (Box Series II-4)
    - Grant, Folder #4 (Box Series II-4)
  - Scorpions Collected in B.G., n.d. (Box Series II-4)
  - Serengeti Research Institute, 1965-1969; n.d. (Box Series II-4)
  - Serengeti Research Institute, 1964, n.d. (Box Series II-4)
  - Shrew. A Proposed Comparative Survey of the Common, n.d. (Box Series II-4)
  - Special Taxonomy. Oxford Course in, 1961 (Box Series II-5)
  - Speciation in the Tropical Environment. Symposium on, 1968 (Box Series II-5)
  - Systematic Zoology, 1979 (Box Series II-5)
  - Systematics Association, 3 folders (Box Series II-5)
    - Folder #1, 1963-1971 (Box Series II-5)
    - Folder #2, 1971-1976 (Box Series II-5)
    - Folder #3, 1977-1984; n.d. (Box Series II-5)
  - Tanganyika Expedition. Oxford University, 1959 (Box Series II-5)
  - Turkey. Oxford Expedition to South Eastern, n.d. (Box Series II-5)
  - Typology in Taxonomy and Anthropology, 1985 (Box Series II-5)
  - U.S. Dept. of Agriculture, n.d. (Box Series II-5)
  - University of Edinburgh. Chair of Forestry and Natural Resources, 1973-1974; n.d. (Box Series II-5)
  - University of Leeds, 1973-1974 (Box Series II-5)
  - University of Liverpool, 5 folders (Box Series II-6)
    - Dept. of Zoology Accounts (Box Series II-6)
      - Folder #1, 1976 (Box Series II-6)
      - Folder #2, 1977 (Box Series II-6)
      - Folder #3, 1978 (Box Series II-6)
      - Folder #4, 1979 (Box Series II-6)
    - Invitations, 1973-1980 (Box Series II-6)
  - Vertebrate Palaeontology and Comparative Anatomy. 21st Symposium of, 1973 (Box Series II-6)
  - Xanthi Symposium, 1985 (Box Series II-6)
  - Zoological Ideas, 1831-1981 (Box Series II-6)
- Series III. Papers by colleagues, 1952-1980; 0.5 boxes; 0.25 linear feet
  A small selection of unpublished papers received by Cain throughout his career. These works are primarily undated typescripts in carbon or photocopy and are filed in this series because they were not found with any accompanying correspondence. Most papers of this nature were originally transmitted to Cain by the authors with letters discussing their contents. In these cases, such unpublished papers were filed in Series I with the correspondence of the author. When no cover letter was found, unpublished papers of colleagues were arranged alphabetically by author's name in Series III.
  - Patterns of molecular variation in plant populations, n.d.; Allard, R.W. and A.L. Kahler (Box Series III-1)
  - Breeding structure of populations: II. Effective population number, 1952; Crow, James F. (James Franklin), 1916- (Box Series III-1)
  - An ornithological survey of the Kidepo National Park, Northern Uganda, Elliott, C.C.H. (Box Series III-1)
  - Area differences in the incidence of neural tube defect and the rate of spontaneous abortion, Frederick, Jean; Frederick, Philippa Adelstein (Box Series III-1)
  - Preceding pregnancy loss as an index of risk of stillbirth or neonatal death in the present pregnancy (Box Series III-1)
  - A new principle of population genetics and its implications for fisheries resource management, Gauldie, R.W. (Box Series III-1)
  - Immunogenetics of trophoblastic tumors, 1976; Lawler, Sylvia D. (Box Series III-1)
  - A removal experiment with sympatric populations of Apodemus sylvaticus (L.) and A. flavicollis (Melchior) (Rodentia: Muridae), Montgomery, W.I. (Box Series III-1)
  - The effect of natural selection on quantitative characters, n.d.; O'Donald, Peter (Box Series III-1)
  - 1980, Unknown (Box Series III-1)
  - The genetics of the Australian sheep blowfly Lucilia cuprina, n.d.; Arnold, James T.; Foster, Geoffrey G.; Konowalow, Christine; Whitten, Maxwell J. (Box Series III-1)